Inventaris van de archieven van de Nederlandse Factorij in Japan te Hirado [1609-1641] en te Deshima, [1641-1860], 1609-1860
Nationaal Archief, Den Haag
These "geschenkgoederen" ("gifts") ought not to be mistaken for the real gifts to the Japanese, handed over on the occasion of the journey to the Shogunal Court.
Cf. inv.nrs. 1161-1305, 1819-1831 and the annexes to inv.nrs. 1431b, seq, 1783-1797, 1803-1818.
The Dutch took due notice of the nature and amount of the Chinese trade to Nagasaki, the Chinese being their only competitors.
In 1685, two thirds of the total import amount were allotted to the Chinese. This distribution roughly corresponded with the existing situation. Cf. Nachod, p. 389 seq.).
With the help of the Japanese, lists with data about the Chinese import and / or export were compiled every year. These lists have been incorporated for the most part in the daily records of the factory.
Cf. the note to inv.nrs. 53-249. See also inv.nrs. 661, 823, 1449g, 1572.
Prices were put in teal's ("thaylen"; "teilen"), initially a Sino-Japanese measure of weight (37,565 grammes), later a standard of value (37.565 grammes of silver). In the trade with the Dutch the so-called "Compagniestael" ('Company's teal') was used as money of account. The value of this teal in the course of years declined from 70 'stuivers' Dutch money (in the 17th century) to 32 'stuivers' (around 1800). For the Kambang-trade a special tael was put into use, which held a higher value. In 1818 the 'Kompstael' was fixed at 40 'stuivers' or 160 'duiten' Dutch Indies money, the Kambangtael at 192 'duiten'. The rate of exchange was accordingly: Dutch guilder: Dutch Indies guilder - 2: 3, Kompstael: Dutch Indies guilder - 3: 4,8.
Nacod, p. 134 seq.; Lauts, p. 283; inv.nrs. 50, 660.
To close this paragraph, something must be said about the tradegoods, imported in or exported from Japan by the Dutch. In the 17th century, raw or spun silk (from China, Siam or Bengal), deerskins, ray hides (from Siam), lead, mercury and sapan-wood were the most importants imports, which were traded against silver, gold, copper, camphor and ( in lesser quantities) lacquerwork and porcelain. From the second half of the 17th century, cotton fabrics from India and several textiles from the Netherlands are of growing importance for the Japanese market. After 1668, when the export of silver was forbidden, the most important Japanese products were copper and camphor. Dutch and Indian textiles, sugar, sapan-wood, lead and tin were the principal imports down to the middle of the 19th century.
The periods 1633-1640 and 1652-1672 were extra-ordinary profitable for the Dutch. In 1636, the profit on import alone amounted to 1,5 million guilders, in 1638 it nearly reached 2,5 million guilders. The importance of the Japanese trade gradually declined, but the United Company did not abandon the factory ( although she threatened to do so several times during the 18th century) for fear that other nations would take her place. The monopoly position was very dear to the company and it was thought that in the course of time matters would change for the better. The importance of the factory after the dissolution of the United Company and the changed attitude towards Japan in the 1840's have been sketched already in par.7.
List of the chief factors, 1609-1860
The data of this list are mainly derived from the daily records of the factory. The persons named are those who actually served as Chief factor (Opper-hoofd), although in some cases they were not appointed as such. After 1641, the given year represents the greater part of the term in office; for instance, '1710' means: October/November 1709 - October/November 1710'. The full dates can be found in the daily records.
Period Chief factor
1609 Sept. 20 - 1613 Febr. 13, Jacques Specx.
1613 Febr. 13 - 1614 Sept. .. Hendrik Brouwer.
1614 Sept. .. - 1621 Jan. .. Jacques Specx.
1621 Jan. .. - 1623 Nov. 21 Leonard Camps.
1623 Nov. 21 - 1932 Dec. .. Cornelis van Neyenroode.
1932 Dec. .. - 1633 Sept. 5 Pieter van Santen.
1633 Sept. 6 - 1939 Febr. 3 Nicolaas Couckebacker.
1939 Febr. 4 - 1641 Febr. 10 François Caron.
1641 Febr. 10 - 1641 Oct. 31 Maximiliaan Lemaire.
1642, 1644 Jan van Elserack
1643, 1645 Pieter Anthonisz Overtwater.
1646 Reinier van Tzum.
1647 Willem Verstegen.
1648 Frederik Coyett.
1649 Dirk Snoek.
1650 Anthony van Brouckhorst.
1651 Pieter Sterthemius.
1652 Adriaan van der Burg.
1653 Frederik Coyett.
1654 Gabriel Happart.
1655 Leonard Winnincx.
1656, 1658, 1660 Joan Bouchelion.
1657, 1659 Zacharias Wagenaar.
1661, 1663 Hendrik Indijk.
1662 Dirk van Lier.
1664, 1666 Willem Volger.
1665 Jacob Gruys.
1667, 1669 Daniel Six
1668 Constantijn Ranst de Jonge.
1670 François de Haase.
1671, 1673, 1675 Martinus Caesar.
1672, 1674, 1676 Johannes Camphuys.
1677, 1679 Dirk de Haas.
1678, 1680 Albert Brevinck.
1681 Isaac van Schinne.
1682 Hendrik Cansius.
1683, 1686 Andries Cleyer.
1684, 1687 Constantijn Ranst de Jonge.
1685, 1688, 1691, 1693; Hendrik van Buytenhem.
1689, 1692, 1696 Cornelis van Outshoorn.
1690 Bathasar Sweers.
1694 Gerrit de Heere.
1695, 1697, 1699, 1701 Hendrik Dijkman.
1698, 1700 Pieter de Vos.
1702 Abraham Douglas.
1703, 1705, 1707 Ferdinand de Groot.
1704 Gideon Tant.
1706, 1708, 1710 Hermanus Mensing.
1709 Jasper van Mansdale.
1711, 1713, 1715 Nicolaas Joan van Hoorn.
1712, 1714 Cornelis Lardijn.
1716 Gideon Boudaen.
1717, 1719 Joan Aouwer.
1718, 1720 Christiaan van Vrijbergen.
1721 Roelof Diodati.
1722, 1723 Hendrik Durven.
1724, 1725 Johannes Thedens.
1726 Joan de Hartogh.
1727, 1729, 1731, 1732 Pieter Bokesteyn.
1728, 1730 Abraham Minnendonk.
1733 Hendrik van der Bel.
1734 Rogier de Laver.
1735 David Drinkman.
1736 Bernardus Coop à Groen.
1737 Jan van der Cruysse.
1738, 1739 Gerardus Bernardus Visscher.
1740, 1742 Thomas van Rhee.
1741, 1743, 1745 Jacob van der Waeyen.
1744 David Brouwer.
1746, 1748 Jan Louis de Win.
1747, 1749 Jacob Balde.
1750, 1752, 1754 Hendrik van Homoed.
1751 Abraham van Suchtelen.
1753, 1755, 1757 David Boelen.
1756, 1758 Herbert Vermeulen.
1759, 1760, 1762 Johannes Reynouts.
1761 Marten Huysvoorn.
1763, 1765 Frederik Willem Wineke.
1764, 1766, 1768, 1769 Jan Crans.
1767 Herman Christiaan Castens.
1770 Olphert Elias.
1771, 1773, 1775 Daniel Armenault.
1772, 1774, 1776, 1778, 1779, 1781 Arend Willem Feith.
1777 Hendrik Godfried Duurkoop.
1780, 1782, 1783 Isaac Titsingh.
1784, 1785, 1787, 1790 Hendrik Casper Romberg.
1786, 1788 Johan Frederik Baron van Reede tot de Parkeler.
1788 dec, 1 - 1789 juli 31 Hendrik Casper Romberg.
1789 aug. 1 - nov. 23 Johan Frederik Baron van Reede tot de Parkeler.
1791, 1792 Petrus Theodorus Chassé.
1793 - 1798 Gijsbert Hemmy.
1799 Leopold Willem Ras.
1800 - 1803 Willem Wardenaar.
1804 - 1817 Hendrik Doeff.
1818 - 1823 Jan Cock Blomhoff.
1824 - 1826 Johan Willem de Sturler.
1827 - 1830 Germain Felix Meylan.
1831 - 1834 Jan Willem Frederik van Citters.
1835 - 1838 Johannes Erdewin Niemann.
1839 - 1842 Edouard Grandisson.
1843 - 1845 Pieter Albert Bik.
1846 - 1850 Joseph Henry Levyssohn.
1851 - 1852 Frederik Cornelis Rose.
1852 - 1860 Jan Hendrik Donker Curtius.
Geschiedenis van het archiefbeheer
1. The transfer of the first part of the archive (1609-1842) to Batavia (1852, 1860) and to the Netherlands (1862/3. The transfer of the second part (1843-1860) to the Netherlands (1909).
By regulation of 17 May 1852 of the Governor-General at Batavia, the Opperhoofd Mr. J.H. Donker Curtius was ordened to send the archive of the factory to Batavia, ".....and this, for the time being, including such a period, as seems to him, after consultation of his predecessor in office, the former Opperhoofd F.C. Rose, proper to be missed on Deshima."
V.R.O.A. 1910, p. 9.
Rose thought that this was the case with the documents anterior to 1800. So this part was sent to the General Secretariat at Batavia, on which consignment Donker Curtius remarks in a covering letter, that the documents written in Japanese (the acts of safe-conduct and others) must be examined first by the Nagasaki officials.
J.H. Donker Curtius to the G.-G., 4 Nov. 1852; inv.nr. 1652.
These Japanese documents were sent to Batavia in September 1860 by the Consul-General of the Netherlands in Japan, together with the lacquered panel with the names of the Opperhoofden
This panel is a Japanse piece of work, made around 1806. In 1850 it was transferred tot the Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam. Cf. Levyssohn, p. 1-28, for a transcript of the contents, and Nachod, p. CXC-CXCIV, for a critical examination.
and with the archive of 1800-1842.
The Government Secretary at Batavia had asked for the transfer of the documents of 1800-1810 or 1800-1815. (Cons.-Gen. Yokohama, inv.nr. 1, nr. 133: Gov. Secr. to Cons.-Gen. in Japan, 1860 April 6; nr. 144: Cons.-Gen. to G.-G., 1860 Sept. 2, with annex: list of consigned documents.) The Consul-General did not mention the reason why the caesura was made at 1842, but this was done probably with a view tot the Shogun in 1844 and the Japanese refusal of the King's presents in 1843. Cf. par. 8, and Van der Chijs, p. 5-66.
At Batavia the archive was preserved on the top floors of the Grain- and Iron-wharehouses, together with documents, produced by other outposts or by the "Hooge Regeering Batavia" ('High Government at Batavia'; henceforth indicated as: H.R.B.). Probably in this period the mixing of the Deshima documents with the last named archive has taken place.
Cf. par.11.
In 1862 and 1863 a part of these collections was sent to the General State Archives at The Hague, after a brief sorting.
V.R.O.A. 1910, p. 9; Ms.-inventory-H.R.B., Intr. p. 1-3.
The Ambassador of the Netherlands at Tokyo finally sent the archive of 1843-1860 to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, (despatch, of 24 June 1909), whence it was received at the General State Archives in October 1909.
V.R.O.A. 1910, p. 9-10; the inventory (by dr. J. de Hullu) on p. 37-48; 397 items.
2. The original order of the archive. The descriptions by Mr. J.E. Heeres and Dr. J. de Hullu.
When the archive covering the period 1609-1799 was transferred to Batavia in 1852, the existing order almost remained unimpaired, which appears from the inscriptions and numbers on the covers of several volumes and from a summary list of the old archive, produced in 1852.
Inv.nr. 1938.
In this list the volumes, quires, bound documents and folders were described invariably as "bundels" (bundles), arranged in comprehensive series 'resolutions', 'daily records', 'incoming and outgoing letters', 'trade books and journals', etc. The documents written in Japanese characters were arranged seperately in chronological order. The same was done with the papers of the years 1800-1842, which remained at the factory for the time being.
Mr. J.E. Heeres has left these arrangements unaltered for the most part in his description of the archive of 1888/1889.
Ms.-inventory on cards by Mr. J.E. Heeres, at the General State Archives, The Hague.
He split up the big series 'incoming and outgoing letters' in incoming and drafts("minuten") of outgoing letters, "letters of the High Government to various out-posts", etc. according to the principle of provenance, while he described the mixed-up documents from the archive of the High Government of Batavia as: "incoming drafts of letters" ("ingekomen minuutbrieven") or: "duplicates of letters received from Japan" The sequence of papers from 1800 till 1842 has been left intact by Heeres, just aswas the case with the group of documents written in Japanese, the account of the factory, etc.
The second part of the archive, (1843-1860), received at the General State Archives in 1909, was described by Dr. J. de Hullu in 1910. He made a division into the archive of the Opperhoofd, the secret archive, etc., and removed the account books, - formerly arranged as annexes to the drafts of outgoing despatches - to separate series concerning trade. This classification has not been done very consistently, the accounts being
dispersed throughout the inventory.
3. The present order of the archive. Deviations from the principle of provenance. The state of preservation.
The present classification and description has been built on the work of Heeres and de Hullu, with due observance of the principle of provenance. The arrangement of resolutions, daily records and other closedseries as those of journals and ledgers was not altered fundamentally. The incoming and outgoing letters lent themselves to a more detailed classification in correspondence with several out-posts or with the Governor-General and his Council, while the letters from or to Japanese authorities were kept apart as far as possible.
A peculiar group is formed by the approved and confirmed drafts ("minuten") of incoming letters and the engrossed copies ("expedities") of outgoing letters from or to Governor-General and Council. These proceed from the archive of the High Government at Batavia, which is proved by inscriptions on the covers of the volumes. To place these items in the H.R.B. - archive, in accordance with the principle of provenance, did not seem desirable, on the one hand because there exists only a fragment of the said archive in the repository of the General State Archives (cf. par.9), on the other hand because these letters fill some gaps in the regular series of Deshima - documents. Inversely, a small number of volume, belonging to the Deshima - archive, got among the H.R.B. - archive. These are mentioned in part F of the inventory, together with the documents that by various causes got among other collections. Of the items, described in Ch. VIII, first period (Incoming documents to the information of the factory) something may also proceed from the H.R.B. - archive, but this cannot be established with certainty.
The items covering the period 1843-1860 were again dealt with separately in the present description. As was remarked in par. 7, the character of the factory was changed during the 1840's which change is shown in the archive by the existence of subdivisions containing secret documents, the papers of Donker Curtius acting as an official envoy, and cash-books, partly relating to the Vice-Consulate on Deshima after February 1860. Therefore it seemed proper to maintain the division of the archive in two periods, connected none the less by a consecutive numeration and a classification that corresponds as much as possible.
The archive, which covers a shelflength of 30 metres, has been preserved on the whole in a good state. A few of the older volumes resolutions, daily records, registers with letters) have suffered from moisture or insects. The documents of the second period have been damaged more, in proportion to their quantity. Those of 1843 are heavenly waterstained or riddled with wormholes, those of 1848 are nearly all missing.
The amount of loose documents is comparatively small; volumes, quires, and sets of bound documents form the greatest part. The bindings of the volumes in the series of correspondence with Governor-General and Council areare often broken, but none the less the volumes are discernible as such.
4. The classification of the trade books in connection with the book-keeping.
The outposts of the United Company had an account current with the "Comptoir-Genereal" (i.e. the Head Office) at Batavia.
Mansfelt,Rechtsvorm, p. 91-92; Glamann, p. 25-252.
The starting point of the book-keeping at the factory was the list of cash money and goods in store, called "Effecten" (Stocks), "Restanten" (Remnants) or "Capitael" (Capital), or - as was the case on Deshima - "Transport van 'sCompanies negotie" (Amount carried of the Company's trade). The account current with Deshima, kept at the Head Office in Batavia, was debited with the amount of this "Capital", just as for the worth of the cargoes to Deshima and for the profits made. On the credit-side were booked the outgoing cargoes, losses, and expenses of the factory. The counter-account at the factory (i.e. the account called "Comptoir-Generaal" on the first folio of the ledger) was credited or debited with these amounts, proceeding from the balances of the several ledger-accounts. At the end end of the trade-season, the account "Comptoir-Generael" was balanced with the "Capital", which sum appears at the head of the credit-side in the factory's ledger of the following season.
In accordance with this procedure the various series of tradebooks are classified. First the general and yearly reports on trade and on thebook-keeping of Deshima are described: nrs. 659-716. Nrs. 717-1120 containthe account-books proper; documents concerning cash amounts, stocks and cargoes; journals and ledgers. The items numbered 1121-1354 are annexes to, orextracts from the journals and ledgers (accounts of profit-and-loss, expenseaccounts), whereas nrs. 1355-1422 concern next year's trade. (Lists of goods in demand and estimates of goods to be imported).
Several of these series end around 1795. This is probably due to careless personnel and disorderly book-keeping rather than to loss of the documents. Matters became still worse with the death of the Opperhoofd GijsbertHemmy during the journey to Edo in 1798. The wharehouse custodian Leopold Willem Ras, who served as a provisional Chief in the next two years, turned out to be unfit for his task. In 1800, the new Opperhoofd Willem Wardenaar straightened the affairs.
Veenhoven, p. 25-26.
Several new types of account and reports were introduced, otherswere disposed of, combined or continued with alterations.
As has been said in par. 10, the archive covering theyears 1800-1842 was arranged chronologically in 1852, the documents of each yearbeing put together in one portfolio. After the removal of resolutions, daily records, reports on trade, incoming and outgoing letters, etc., a number of pieces concerning the book-keeping remained, which were not suited to aclassification in series. This is the case particularly with the papers from 1800 to 1830. It may be said to be partly a result of Wardenaar's doings.Therefore the chronological arrangement was maintained, a descriptive list beingmade of the contents of each unit: inv.nrs. 1423-1463.
The classification of the trade books from 1843 to 1860 has been done in accordance with the principles explained in the first part of this aragraph. The so-called "rekening-courant" ( the term appears in 1818) is not an account current with Batavia, but must be called a cash-balance ( kas-rekening).
5. Entries and expedients for the use of the archive.
In a number of cases, tables of contents ('tafels'), post-books ('agenda's') and indexes ('indices'; 'klappers') are extant in the volumes of resolutions, daily records, letters and reports, wich is mentioned in a note to the item concerned. Inv. nrs. 356-425 and 503-528 contain lists of incoming and outgoing letters and annexes, often not in accordance with the actual contents of the volumes. Inv. nr. 52 is a loose repertory ('repertorium') with an index ('klapper') on orders from Gentlemen Seventeen and Goverenor-General and Council. Such repertories, partly proceeding from the Deshima-archive, are to be found in the archive-H.R.B. (Cf. Part F). Inv.nr. 1572 contains a very concise and inaccurate summary of the documents presented at Deshima in 1826, with some notes about the volumes then missing. Inv.nr. 1938 gives a complete summary of the documents, transferred from Deshima in 1852, whereas inv. nr. 1688 is a detailed inventory of the secret archive.
The article by T. Itazawa
Cf. the list of quoted sources and literature for the books and articles mentioned in this and the following paragraph.
includes a name-list of the Opperhoofden, with the dates of the daily records produced during their term in office, covering the period 1631-1860. M. Kanai in his contribution on Donker Curtius not only deals with the transfer of the Deshima archive to the Netherlands but gives also a survey of Dutch archival sources relating to Japan, and of Dutch archival management and institutions.
At the Historiographical Institute (Shiryo Hensan-jo) of the University of Tokyo a series of volumes about historical documents relating to Japan in foreign countries is in the course of production; five volumes wil be dedicated to the documents about Japan, Formosa and China, reposing is the General State Archives. Volume I, part I of these five has appeared already in 1963. This volume contains a detailed survey of the Deshima-archive as far as it was transferred to Batavia in 1852. (1614-1800, with the daily records extending to 1831). The items were mentioned in the order, adopted by Heeres in his ms.-inventory, (Cf. par. 10), with a descriptive list of each item added. The survey is partly in Dutch (caption titles being copied from the documents), partly in English. The portfolio-numbers of 'Heeres' inventory are mentioned also. Therefore, to facilitate the use of the present inventory together with the survey, a concordance of inventory-numbers and portfolio-numbers has been given hereafter. The former numeration of the documents from 1843-1860 (inventory by Dr. J. de Hullu) is placed between brackets.
6. Publication of documents from the archive.
In the works of Van Dam, Valentijn, Montanus, Kaempfer, Nachod, Feenstra Kuiper etc. a great number of documents relating to the Dutch in Japan have been printed, the provenance of which cannot be established with certainty, at least not in the case of the older works mentioned. The editors of the Corpus Diplomaticum Neerlando-Indicum have used copies of documents from the Deshima-archive, which copies repose in other archives and collections. (With one exception: inv.nr. 646). Veenhoven in his thesis edited parts of inv.nrs. 275, 430, 435. 437/8, 533, 548, 542/5 as annexes.
The publication of inv.nrs. 50, 276, 646, 660, 1470, and 1602/3 is mentioned in the notes of the items concerned.
A survey of Japanese activity in this field naturally can be only cursory. N. Murakami edited abstracts of the daily records of the periods 1641 June 25 - 1645 November 29 and 1650 October 25 - 1654 October 31 in a Japanese translation; the edition of the 'Japans Dagh Register' by "Nichi-ran Koshoshi Kenkyukai" is mentioned in the list of quoted sources and literature and in a note to the daily records in the present inventory. The monumental series of publications by the Historiographical Institute mentioned above, may contain some Deshima-documents in a Japanese translation. (E.g. the "Dai Nippon Shiryo": Chronological Source-books of Japanese History from the 9th Century to the 19th Century).
De verwerving van het archief
Het archief is bij Koninklijk Besluit of ministeriële beschikking overgebracht.
Aanwijzingen voor de gebruiker
Openbaarheidsbeperkingen
Volledig openbaar.
Materiële beperkingen
Het archief kent beperkingen voor het raadplegen van stukken als gevolg van slechte materiële staat.
A small number of papers in these archives is in a bad physical condition, as a consequence of which they cannot be applied for. A survey of the inventory numbers in question has been omitted here, because the physical condition and the resultant application possibilities are not of a permanent character (preservation, microfilming etc.). If applicable, you will be noted when applying by way of the terminal.
Aanvraaginstructie
Openbare archiefstukken kunnen online worden aangevraagd en gereserveerd. U kunt dit ook via de terminals in de studiezaal van het Nationaal Archief doen. Om te kunnen reserveren dient u de volgende stappen te volgen:
Creëer een account of log in.
Selecteer in de archiefinventaris een archiefstuk.
Klik op ‘Reserveer’ en kies een tijdstip van inzage.
Verwant materiaal
Beschikbaarheid van kopieën
Inventarisnummers van dit archief zijn in kopievorm beschikbaar
Bijlagen
Concordance
First period